<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>TCF112-900 UA Summer 2016</title>
    <description>Notes and materials websites to go along with the online course TCF 112 taught summer 2016 at The University of Alabama
</description>
    <link>http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 23:40:06 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 23:40:06 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Narrative Video Lecture</title>
        <description>&lt;script&gt;
$(function() {
  new AudioNavigator({
    videoId: &quot;169177289&quot;
  });
})
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;module-2---narrative-and-story&quot;&gt;Module 2 - Narrative and Story&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-life-so-far&quot;&gt;My Life So Far&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your life is more than likely a good story which could be a movie&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much do you put in the film?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:02:08.505241&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;raw-material&quot;&gt;Raw Material&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The story has to be carved up into the movie&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The story is the raw Material&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The plot is how it is chopped up to be a movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-parts-of-the-story-do-we-use-in-our-plot&quot;&gt;What parts of the story do we use in our plot?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One goal of filmmaking is keeping the viewers engaged
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is done by withholding information
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This makes people curious and want to know what’s going to happen&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:05:03.025469&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Film raises short term and long term Questions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Only reveals enough to keep us curious&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;formal-analysis-exercise-narration-within-a-scene&quot;&gt;Formal Analysis Exercise: Narration within a scene&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dark Knight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:05:51.136502
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What questions are you asking yourself?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Who’s that guy holding the mask?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:06:26.170841&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Why are they ziplining?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:06:42.252460&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ohh they’re going to do a heist and the Joker is involved&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:07:31.575395&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Which one of these characters is the Joker?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;They are robbing a bank&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:08:29.601599&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When is Batman going to show up?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:08:57.570866&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What? Why did the bad guy shoot the bad guy?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:09:38.512296&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;That dude just shot that guy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:10:39.726652&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The bad guy just got electrocuted?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:11:04.573081&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;He’s out right?
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;What’s that mean!?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:12:09.222831&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ohh he’s out of shots&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The bad guy was electrocuted by a trap&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This bank is under the control of the mob&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:13:09.845331&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Who are these guys?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Where’s the joker?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oh they’re shooting each other to get more money&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:14:08.366699&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bus driver?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oh that bus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oh shit that’s the Joker
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:15:33.252514&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How is this about to kill the bank employee?
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:16:17.063760&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Wow it’s just smoke&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-should-viewers-care-about-your-characters&quot;&gt;Why should viewers care about your characters?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Film makers have to create a world from scratch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:18:06.091876&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ex: Up (Disney)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First few minutes function as a way to get the viewers to care about the characters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the viewers care about the characters, it’s more likely that the viewers will keep watching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:19:16.532052&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In some cases, the plot starts with what happens to the character at the end of the story
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;all of this is to increase your investment in the film&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;depth-of-narration&quot;&gt;Depth of Narration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shallow narration
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Only gives you access to what the characters know&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deep Narration
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Readers are given access to character’s thoughts and other information&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most films uses shallow narration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:21:42.595443&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;range-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;Range of Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When do the viewers know what the characters know&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A restricted range of knowledge can be used to deliver a shock when the viewer witnesses what a character experiences as it happens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scene-in-starwars-from-last-lecture&quot;&gt;Scene in starwars from last Lecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:24:43.513187&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Range of Knowledge
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We know more than Luke and friends know&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We know more than the droids&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dramatic irony: the audience knows something that the characters don’t&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-brief-history-of-narrative-in-film&quot;&gt;A Brief History of Narrative in film&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1900-1920’s
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No sound, and small budgets&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:26:19.819716&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Probably only told highlights of well-known stories&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1927-1950’s
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dialog conveys information&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No stories with nudity, swaring, or “bad guys” winning&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Law: the Production code of 1930&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1950’s - 1980’s
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Global travel and trade&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;European art films tended to focus on an individual’s life&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1970’s: Hollywood films are influenced by the art cinema&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1980’s - present
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blockbusters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Large events&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thrill ride narratives&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Adhere to tried and true formulas because they spend huge amount off money and can’t take chances&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Popular alternative narratives&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:30:46.508538&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Term&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Definition&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;story&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The raw material of a film&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;plot&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;How the story is chopped up to be a movie&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/06/02/narrative-video-lecture.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/06/02/narrative-video-lecture.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>syllabus</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;tcf-112-motion-picture-history-and-criticism---section-900-online&quot;&gt;TCF 112: Motion Picture History and Criticism - Section 900 (online)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Summer 2016&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;May 31 - June 30&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dr. Elliot Panek: epanek@ua.edu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Course Description &amp;amp; Objectives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Before YouTube and Netflix, before television, there was film. Film was the first means by which humans communicated through moving pictures. Though many assumed or feared that film would be displaced by television, home video (VHS and then DVD), or the internet, movies continue to be an essential part of the global cultural landscape and our individual media diets. Why have they persisted? How and why have they changed over the years? How have we sought to understand their power to reshape consciousness, to start revolutions, or to give us something fun to do on a Saturday night? This online course uses a combination of highly interactive methods of instruction to help you to answer these questions for yourselves. Through an interactive version of a textbook, frequent quiz questions, video lectures, feature-length film viewing, and online discussions, you will develop a knowledge set that you can apply to understanding all types of motion pictures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;course-learning-objectives&quot;&gt;Course Learning Objectives:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After completing this course, you should be able to:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Understand the basic elements of films
Explain how and why film conventions changed over the years
Understand why filmmakers make various creative choices
Know the main theories of film criticism (e.g., Auteur theory) from 1900-2015
Experience enjoyment and enrichment from a broad range of films from a range of eras and a variety of cultures&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;text&quot;&gt;Text:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Smartbook” version of Film Art: An Introduction, 11th Edition. David Bordwell, Kristin Thompson, Jeff Smith. McGraw Hill Education. Access through McGraw Hill Connect and UA Blackboard Learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;films&quot;&gt;Films:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citizen Kane (1941)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psycho (1960)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Singin in the Rain (1957)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sunrise: A Song of Two Humans (1929)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hoop Dreams (1994)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Searchers (1956)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 400 Blows (1959)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-components-and-schedule&quot;&gt;Learning Components and Schedule:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This online course is modeled after the offline version of TCF 112. It covers the same amount of material and counts for the same number of credits. To cover the material during the shortened Summer 1 semester, we must cover two online lessons - referred to as “modules” - per week. From June 2nd to June 30th, every Tuesday and Thursday, you will be responsible for completing the following learning components:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Assignment&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Approximate Duration&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Complete the assigned reading&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(30-60 mins)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Complete quiz on reading&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(10-20 mins)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Watch lecture video&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(20-30 mins)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Watch feature film (if applicable)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(90-160 mins)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Complete quiz on lecture and film&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(10 mins)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Post in the Discussion Forum&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;(15-30 mins)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total Time to Complete Each Module&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3 to 6 hours per module&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More detailed information about each module, including the specific activities for which you are responsible and the date on which the material is due, is provided below. All material is due at 11:59pm on the date specified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 5/31 
Introduction Module: How the Course Works, and How we will Talk about Film&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: This module is designed as an introduction to online course format, how to access materials, how to complete assignments. You will watch a brief video that introduces you to the learning components of the course. You will also watch a video that introduces you to the way in which you will be watching and discussing film in this course. There are many, many ways to analyze and discuss film. In order to proceed, we all need to “be on the same page” and decide what elements or attributes of film we are analyzing for each module. To do this, we need to narrow our focus to two specific attributes of film - its form and its content. This module is designed to help students understand the difference between film form and film content. The course lecture video also provides several examples of how to analyze a film’s form and several examples of how to analyze its content. It also introduces the concept of “critical viewing”, makes explicit how it differs from our ordinary experience with films, and provides students an opportunity to try out this new way of looking at film scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Download and review syllabus and course schedule
	Watch the welcome video
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Participate in introductions on the discussion forum  (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)
	Obtain textbook and access to the films we will watch (see above)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/2
Module 2: Narrative and Story&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: Film is primarily a storytelling medium. In fact, many say that it is most powerful, popular means of storytelling ever devised. Surely, the content of the story accounts for part of whether or not it interests an audience. However, there are many ways in which the form of the story, or narrative, takes shape that influence viewers’ reactions to films. This module introduces students to the concepts of plot, story, and story structure. We examine specific choices made by filmmakers as to how to tell a story using motion pictures. In particular, we look at: whose point of view do we see the action? What is the order in which events in the story are presented via the plot? Are we restricted to a particular character’s knowledge of diegetic events or can we know more than particular characters? How much do we know about character’s internal states?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand the elements of the traditional Hollywood “continuity editing” style of storytelling
	Understand how that style has evolved and been modified
	Being able to identify particular choices made by filmmakers vis a vis the story of the film and knowing how these choices affect viewers’ emotional experience&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Complete the reading: Chapter 3 from Film Art
	Complete Chapter 3 Quiz
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Complete quiz on the lecture
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/7
Module 3: Mise En Scene &amp;amp; Cinematography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: Aside from being a storytelling medium, film is also a visual medium. This sets it apart from the novel, the radio play, and other forms of popular storytelling that preceded it. As with narrative structure, the choices made by filmmakers influence the emotions and levels of interest of viewers, often in subtle ways. This module introduces students to the concepts related to the visual look of films, specifically mise en scene and cinematography. We examine specific choices made by filmmakers as to how to show things on screen. In particular, we look at: what is included in the frame? What is the distance between the camera and the subject? How is the subject lit? How are characters oriented toward one another in the frame? How do objects move through the frame? How does the camera move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand the options filmmakers have as to how to depict a subject visually in motion pictures
	Understand how that process has evolved and been modified across time and across different filmmaking traditions (e.g., Japanese cinema)
	Being able to identify particular choices made by filmmakers vis a vis visual aspects of the film and knowing how these choices affect viewers’ emotional experience&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Complete the reading: Chapters 4 &amp;amp; 5 from Film Art
	Complete Chapters 4 and 5 Quizzes
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Watch this module’s film: Citizen Kane (1941)
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lecture and film
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/9
Module 4: Editing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: One moment, viewers are in a well-appointed room in England, and the next, they find themselves in the middle of the Arabian desert. How is it that viewers understand what has happened? How does editing allow filmmakers (and viewers) to conquer space and time? We’ve discussed how films tell visual stories, but film is more than just the marriage of story and image. In nearly every case, films are a series of different images stitched together through the process of editing. This module introduces students to the way in which the juxtaposition of two images creates a “third meaning”, and how the pace at which filmmakers’ switch from image to image affects our perceptions and emotions. We continue to examine specific choices made by filmmakers as to how to tell a story using motion pictures. In particular, we look at: how diegetic space and time are constructed through a process of editing; how editing can be used to situate the viewer in the place of a character, heightening character identification; the larger implications of enhanced character identification through editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand the options filmmakers have as to how to edit particular scenes in a film
	Understand how that process has evolved and been modified across time and across different filmmaking traditions (e.g., Soviet-era Russian films)
	Being able to identify particular choices made by filmmakers vis a vis editing and knowing how these choices affect viewers’ emotional experience (in particular, the experiences of immersion in a diegetic world and character identification)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Complete the reading: Chapter 6 from Film Art
	Complete Chapter 6 quiz
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Watch this module’s film: Psycho (1960)
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lecture and film
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/14
Module 5: Sound&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: By the 1920’s, many of the fundamental elements of filmmaking were in use around the world. Then came the invention of recorded sound. Though we take synchronized sound in film for granted, there was a time when many critics felt it would ruin motion picture storytelling. How would the visual vocabulary of filmmaking change when this technological innovation was introduced? And what does this moment in film history have to teach us about the successes (color film) and failures (3D film) of technological innovation in filmmaking? This module introduces students to the way in which sound has been used to affect viewers’ emotional experience. We typically consider film to be a visual medium, but sound plays a significant (often subtle) role in viewers’ experience of film. We continue to examine specific choices made by filmmakers as to how to tell a story using motion pictures. In particular, we look at: how the juxtaposition of image and sound creates a “third meaning”; how sound is used to enhance realism; how the introduction of sound changed other aspects of film (e.g., editing, the types of stories that were told, mise en scene).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand the options filmmakers have as to how to create a “soundscape” for a film
	Consider how and why other technologies (e.g., color, 3D) have become integrated or failed to become integrated into the filmmaking process
	Being able to identify particular choices made by filmmakers vis a vis editing and knowing how these choices affect viewers’ emotional experience (in particular, the experiences of immersion in a diegetic world and character identification)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Complete the reading: Chapter 7 from Film Art
	Complete Chapter 7 quiz
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Watch this module’s film: Singin in the Rain (1952)
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lecture and film
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/16
Module 6: Acting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: It can be difficult to discuss acting in an objective way. Too often, the merit of one’s acting is conflated with aspects of the role taken on by the actor (in particular, how physically and emotionally taxing the role was on the actor). Things become clearer when we consider acting, just like any other aspect of filmmaking, as a series of choices. This module introduces students to the challenge of considering the very subtle choices film actors make and how those choices affect viewers’ emotional experience (in particular character identification and realism). In particular, we look at: what actors do with their faces, voices, and bodies; how the introduction of sound altered actors’ performances; how the introduction of “method acting” changed viewers’ perceptions of film realism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand the options actors have when performing a role on screen
	Consider the concept of “realism” as it relates to acting (i.e., how cultures differ in terms of how emotions are expressed, and how we must reconcile the concept of realism with this fact)
	Be able to spot very subtle changes in actors’ faces, voices, and the use of their bodies to affect viewers in a particular way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Watch this module’s film: Sunrise: A Song of Two Humans (1929)
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lesson
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/21
Module 7: Documentary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: Though this course does not consider the many different genres of film over the decades (e.g., horror, science fiction, comedy, melodrama), it is worth making a distinction between two types of film: fiction and non-fiction, also known as documentary films. This module introduces students to a distinct type of film: documentaries. This type of film has some elements in common with other types of films (they typically have characters with whom viewers are meant to identify) while possessing other unique attributes (they are perceived as being more “real” than fiction films). In particular, we look at: the importance of editing in documentary filmmaking (what to include, what to leave out); different types of documentaries (explanatory documentaries vs. persuasive documentaries); the ethical implications of documentary filmmaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand the ways in which documentary filmmakers manipulate images of reality to present a particular perspective
	Be aware of the ethical implications of using real people in documentaries
	Be aware of the formal similarities and differences between fictional narrative films and documentary films&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Complete the reading: The “Documentary” portion of Chapter 10 in Film Art
	Complete Chapter 10 Documentary quiz
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Watch this module’s film: Hoop Dreams (1994)
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lecture and film
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/23
Module 8: Experimental Film&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: This module introduces students to another distinct type of film: experimental films. This type of film often proves challenging for first-time viewers; often, experimental filmmakers are deliberately going against traditional mechanisms of character identification and realism, deliberately frustrating viewers’ desires. Yet, for the viewer who is willing to experience something new, this module can open one’s mind to the possibilities (many of which have yet to be explored) of the motion picture, and to realize that despite over 100 years of film history, we have yet to scratch the surface in terms of how films can be used to affect viewers. The module is designed to introduce students to a totally different kind of film to help them understand how vast the possibilities are in terms of what motion pictures can do. In particular, we look at: what types of effects experimental filmmakers are trying to achieve in viewers; how they use the formal elements of film (editing, story structure, character) in unique ways to achieve those effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand that not all films seek to immerse the viewers in a diegetic world or have them identify with characters
	Be aware of the way in which film can be used in a playful formal way, or can be used to question the ways in which traditional filmmaking “manipulates” viewers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Complete the reading: The “Documentary” portion of Chapter 10 in Film Art
	Complete Chapter 10 Experimental quiz
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lecture
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/28
Module 9: Theme, Meaning, and Sub-Text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: Thus far, we have discussed matters of film form: how choices made by filmmakers as to HOW to show something affect viewers. Many modules made the assumption that viewers react in more or less the same way to films. Of course, there is more to it than that. Film viewing, like reading, is a matter of interpretation, and not all of us interpret a single text (be it a film text or a print text) the same way. This module introduces students to questions related to a film’s meaning. It treats meaning as something that does not reside in the film nor is it something that is dictated by the filmmakers’ stated intentions, but rather something that is co-created by the filmmaker, the film, and the viewer. Students are dissuaded from trying to find the one, true meaning of a film, and encouraged to acknowledge the virtues of considering multiple meanings of films. This perspective can help viewers understand themselves and the world around them as well as the films themselves. In particular, we look at: how people discuss the “meaning” of a film; the difference between manifest and latent meaning; how to consider the relationship between the film and the culture in which it was produced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Understand how to discuss the latent meaning of a film
	Understand that not all viewers will understand a particular film in the same way, but that they are likely to share particular interpretations with some other viewers in predictable ways
	Grasp the power of film (in particular the ability to see parallels between a film and the world outside of the film) to enhance viewers’ understanding of themselves and the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Watch this module’s film: The Searchers (1956)
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lesson
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DUE 11:59, 6/30
Module 10: Popular Critical Approaches to Film&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overview: By now, you should have a grasp of the basic principles of film form, content, and meaning. This final module introduces students to various film criticism traditions. In a sense, the students have been engaging in film criticism in all of the modules, but this module reviews particular popular ways of looking at, writing about, and discussing films. In particular, we look at: Auteur theory (how it developed; what it says about film authorship; why it matters), cultural theory (how both form and content of films reflect and alter the culture in which they are produced), feminist theory (how character identification in the film viewing experience alters viewers’ experience of sex and gender beyond the film).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Objectives: Upon the completion of this module, students should be able to: 
	Be familiar with the most popular strains of film criticism
	Be able to analyze a scene from a film using these traditions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities: 
	Complete the reading: Chapter 11 from Film Art
	Complete Chapter 11 quiz
	Watch this module’s lecture video
	Watch this module’s film: The 400 Blows (1959)
	Complete quiz questions associated with this module’s lecture and film
	Participate in online discussion forum associated with this module’s lesson (see Blackboard Discussion Board for detailed instructions)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/05/31/syllabus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/05/31/syllabus.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lecture 1 - Form, Content, Meaning no reading or quiz</title>
        <description>&lt;div style=&quot;position:fixed;bottom:1em;right:1em; background:black;padding:.5em&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 style=&quot;margin:0;color:white&quot;&gt;Navigate using audio&lt;/h2&gt;
	&lt;div id=&quot;player&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
new AudioNavigator({
	videoId: &quot;_YGQnS4vFEk&quot;
});
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 12:01:04.696809&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;module-1-understanding-form-content-and-meaning&quot;&gt;Module 1: Understanding Form, Content, and Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turning off auto-pilot
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We like to get sucked in by movies
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;For this course, we need to fight against this and focus on specific elements of a film&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are many different ways to talk about film&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elements-well-discuss&quot;&gt;Elements we’ll discuss&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Form vs. Content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The information being conveyed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The story&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;form&quot;&gt;Form&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The manor in which a story is conveyed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Father dies, seaks revenge
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hamlet&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lion King&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Roughly the same form and diologue, but the form is diferent&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-example&quot;&gt;Content example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Son of wealthy man witnesses murder of parents and grows up to become a vigilante to stop crime in his city
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Batman has been told many ways&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:04:44.064035&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;differences-of-form&quot;&gt;Differences of form&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:06:05.069722&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sound effects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;formal-analysis-exercise-1-cutting-on-the-action&quot;&gt;Formal Analysis Exercise 1: Cutting on the Action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:06:38.725237&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real life doesn’t change perspective, but film does it all the time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Film wants you to forget that you’re not actually experiencing this
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;However, cutting is not at all like real life&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The continuity of action prevents you from questioning it&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The audio also forms a bridge over the cuts&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cutting in an action sequence
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:09:54.331215
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Happens a lot&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The Born Supremacy has a ton of cuts&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“Good” editing
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Depends on the norm&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;formal-analysis-exercise-2-editing-patterns&quot;&gt;Formal Analysis Exercise 2: Editing patterns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:11:57.186163&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Girl on phone&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;B
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Guy on phone&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Girl on phone&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;line-of-action&quot;&gt;Line of action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cutting back and forth between two parallel events (with
  their own cuts)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:13:30.444957&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Look at Star Wars: A New Hope (1977)
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Watch for lines of action in different locations&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;A: the scene in the trash compactor&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;B: the scene with the droids and clones
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;While in scene B, you are acutely aware that our heroes
  are going to be crushed in scene A
                &lt;ul&gt;
                  &lt;li&gt;Will c3p0 shut down the garbage compactor in time?&lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;/ul&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pace-of-the-editing&quot;&gt;Pace of the editing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pace in the Star Wars scene speeds up as the tension builds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The music and sound effects also affect this scene&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;narrative-structure&quot;&gt;Narrative Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Important events in the story prompt viewers to ask questions about what Will happen
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Is he/she/it going to die?”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:19:13.981848&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“What’s going to happen next?”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narrative Structure of Star Wars: A New Hope (1977)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;leia sends out a message
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Will she survive&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;luke goes to find her
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Will he find her?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;luke’s aunt and uncle killed
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;What will he do?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Teams up with Solo and Chewy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vader captures Luke and friends&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Solo leaves&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Luke discovers weakness of Death Star and Han returns&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Death star destroyed
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;He will win&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;narrative-structure-of-american-beauty-1999&quot;&gt;Narrative Structure of American Beauty (1999)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main character Lester dies
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How did he die? Who killed him?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:22:30.177011&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You gradually receive information about how the events happened&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A boy is threatening to kill his girlfriend’s Father
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Did he do it?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Father is dead
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Looks like he did it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lester’s wife is angry
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Did she do it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ricky’s father killed Lester
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Oh he did it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;forrest-gump-1994&quot;&gt;Forrest Gump (1994)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gump waits for bus
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Who is he?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gump actually leads impressive life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gump visits Jenny
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Will he get together with Jenny?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;all-is-lost-2013&quot;&gt;All is Lost (2013)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:25:05.858779
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Who is this guy?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How did he mess up?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Why is he apologizing?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How did he get lost at sea?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We spend most of the movie seeing how he got to point A&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writes letter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main character tries to survive
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What’s going to happen?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;syllabus-schedule&quot;&gt;Syllabus Schedule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Module 2: Narrative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Module 3: Visual Aspects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-meaning-of-films&quot;&gt;The meaning of films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goes beyond the simple content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goes beyond the form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meaning usually refers to hidden, implicit messages embedded in the film
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;And how they relate to us&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audio 0:29:27.980858&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tricky to talk about meaning of film
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heavily relies on culture&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;First we will talk mostly on form&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/05/31/lecture-1-form-content-meaning-no-reading-or-quiz.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/05/31/lecture-1-form-content-meaning-no-reading-or-quiz.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Intro Video</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VrzzPnQz3tA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/05/31/intro-video.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jmbeach.github.io/TCF112-900/2016/05/31/intro-video.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
